Teyla，这儿你熟悉吗？
Anything look familiar to you Teyla?
不，我想我以前没有来过这儿
No, I do not think this is a world I have visited before.
这儿也没什么显著标志，你是怎么判断的？
Without landmarks, how can you tell?
我们在天上很难判断
但每个星球都有自己独特的一面
It is difficult by air, but every
world is unique in it's own way.
我看过很多来自SG部队的报告
就是关于这样的行动的
I've heard a lot of reports from SG teams,
on missions like this one.
特别是Samantha Carter上校的行动报告
Specifically the mission reports
of Colonel Samantha Carter.
几年前，我和她一起工作过
参加一个阻止地球灾难的行动
She and I worked together to avert
global catastrophe a few years back,
我还和她……
and she and I ...
我刚说到哪了？
What was I saying?
行动报告
Mission reports.
好吧，很明显，有生命存在的星球
都有很多令人惊异的相似之处
Right. Well apparently, there's remarkable
similarities between worlds that support life.
有道理，例如天空的颜色，就是……
It makes sense really
For example, the colour of the sky, which is a product...
那是什么？
What was that?
湍流?
Turbulence?
现在好像没事了，我在想刚刚发生什么事了？
Seems to be ok now. I wonder what that was?
出现一个严重冲突的数据
Getting seriously conflicting readings.
看起来像是一个强大的能量场
大约2000码远
Looks like some sort of powerful energy field,
about 2000 yards over there.
在哪儿？
Over where?
在我们正前方18度
18 degrees from our correct heading.
有必要检查一下吗？
Is it worth checking out?
任何重要的能量数据都意味着技术进步
Any significant energy reading,
generally means technological civilisation.
所以你觉得有必要检查
So you think it's worth checking out.
不错，能量场看起来很稳定
I'm sorry. Yes. Energy field good.
也许不是
Maybe not
越来越糟了
It's getting worse.
行了，我要离开这儿了
That's enough, I'm getting out of here.
我们没有海拔显示了
We're not gaining any altitude.
控制系统失灵了
Controls are unresponsive.
驱动器掉线了
The drive just went offline.
我们要进去了
We're going in!
星际之门之亚特兰蒂斯
第一季第6集 童年的终结
Season 1 : Episode 6
Childhood's End
先生，安全着陆
Nice landing sir.
谢谢
Thankyou
发生什么事了？
What happened?
我们离能量场太近了
We got too close to the energy field.
谁出的主意
Who's idea was that?
你犯错，我也犯错
You made mistakes, I made mistakes.
咱俩就狗咬狗吧
Let's not get caught in the blame game.
好吧，你到底能不能修好飞船？
Ok, can you fix the ship or not?
我的检测仪器都失灵了
None of my diagnostic equipment is working.
太阳依然悬挂在天空
The sun is still high in the sky.
什么意思？
What does that mean?
我们能在天黑之前回到星门
We can make it back to the Stargate before dark.
如果我们想离开，现在就要行动了
If we intend to leave, we should start now.
你和Zelenka能回去修好它吗？
Zelenka and you can return to fix it?
不，不，少校，你不明白
No, no, no Major. You don't understand.
这不是飞船的问题，我的设备在这儿一个也无法使用
It's not just the jumper. None of my equipment is working either.
好吧，加油
Alright. Let's gear up.
检查一下，长官。
我觉得我的指南针开始摇摆不定
Check it out sir. I think my compass has gone wonky.
你把磁力指南针带到了
另外一个星系的星球上？
You brought a magnetic compass
to another planet in another galaxy?
你完全不知道这个星球的磁场是否……
You have absolutely no way of knowing
if this planets magnetic field is....
等一会
Wait a second.
让我看看
Let me see that.
摇摆不定是由电磁引起的
The disturbance is electro-magnetic.
这也许能解释为什么我们的设备都失效了
That probably explains why all our equipment is out.
星门在哪个方位
Which direction is the gate?
你是驾驶员你还不知道？
You were the one flying. Shouldn't you know?
好，我应该能辨别出来
Alright. Should be able to figure this out.
我认为是在这个方位
I believe it is this way.
出发吧
Let's move out.
嗨！我们能往那边走吗？
Hey! Can we go that way for a bit?
为什么？
Why?
Ford中尉的指南针指向很怪异
我们可能有点误差
Lt Ford's compass is acting weird.
We may be onto something.
真高兴，我把指南针带到这里了
I'm glad I brought it along.
你还挺有先见之明的
How prescient of you.
哦耶，是这个方向
Didn't fly over this
我们飞来的时候经过这儿了吗？
on the way in did we?
我不知道，那时候我正注意观察周围
可能袭击我们的东西
I don't know. I was kinda busy with
the whole trying not to get us killed thing.
这些古迹年代很久远了
These ruins are very old.
至少几百年了，我敢说，也许更久
Several hundred years at least, I'd say, maybe more.
所以这里的居民已经绝迹了
So the population here's extinct?
看看这个
Check this out.
我放弃了
Ok, I give up.
如果这种摇摆是人为原因
而不是自然现象
Well if the disturbance is man made
instead of naturally occurring,
那就很可能是这些古迹中的放射性物质造成的
it's probably emanating from within these ruins.
在那里
Somewhere over there.
如果我们找到它，能关掉吗？
Well if we find it, can we shut it off?
如果我们能关掉能量场，那就值得一试
Well it's worth a shut. If we can shut down the field,
那我们就能回到星门
we can walk back to the gate.
我正在想给自己留一个最好的飞船
I was thinking of saving a perfectly good puddle jumper.
我也想
That too.
好吧，兄弟们
我们在这呆一会，看看McKay是否能够……
Alright guys.
Let's stay here for a second, see if McKay can....
Ford，他们只是小孩
They're kids Ford.
用武器指着我们的小孩
Yeah, with weapons pointed at us.
中尉，把你的武器放低点
Lower your weapon Lt.
你们好，孩子们
Hey kids.
我们不会伤害你们的
We're not here to harm you in any way.
没错，就像她说的那样
That's right. What she she said.
我们很友好
We're friendly, ok?
我们穿过星门来到这儿
We arrived through the Stargate.
只是想回到我们来的地方
We were only trying to return home.
我想他们听不懂
I don't think they understand.
我相信他们听得懂
I believe they do.
他们仍然拿箭指着我们
They're still pointing arrows at us.
你们是成年人
You're full grown.
什么？
Excuse me?
你们需要去见长者
You need to see the elders
长者，听起来不错，你们带路吧
Elders. Sounds good. Just lead the way.
成年人？
Full growns?
少校
Major
他们从哪儿弄到这些东西的？
Now where did they get that?
看起来像个神龛
It looks like a shrine
你觉得他们应该不会供奉幽灵吧
You don't think they worship the Wraith do you?
-极有可能
-这就麻烦了
- That would be a first.
- It would be disturbing.
幽灵的骨头
Wraith bones.
是的，我们知道
Yeah, we know
这是几年前从天上掉下来的幽灵船
It's death boat fell out of the sky, years ago.
我们把它留在这儿，提醒我们别忘了过去的生活
We keep it here to remind us of how life used to be.
过去？
Used to be?
从前
Before
从天上掉下来
Fell out of sky.
哦，我注意到了
Yeah, I picked up on that.
你觉得击落它的东西也就是击落我们的东西吗？
You think whatever knocked us down, knocked it down?
很有可能。如果真是这样，我们需要找到它
It's possible. If that's the case, we need to find it.
为什么
Why?
因为有什么东西有那么大的力量
能把幽灵击落？肯定是个好东西
Because anything powerful enough
to knock out a Wraith dart? It's a big deal.
是啊，我们要是能拥有就好了
Yeah, that would be nice to have.
长者准备见你们了
The elders are ready.
嗨，很荣幸见到你
Hi, nice to meet you.
我是Karris，这里的长者之一
I am Karris. One of the village elders
我是Sheppard，这是Rodney和Teyla和……
I'm Sheppard, and this is Rodney and Teyla and....
你刚刚说你是这里的长者之一？
Did you say you were one of the elders?
是的
Yes
你多大了
How old are you?
24岁
24岁就是长者？
That makes you an elder?
Sheppard，你怎么到这儿的？
How did you get here Sheppard?
我们通过星门从我们的星球来到这儿的
We used the Stargate to travel
from our world, to visit yours.
你应该知道星门
You do know of the Stargate.
这是一个大大的、圆圆的东西
It's a big round....thing.
500年来都没有人从那个大井里穿行了
No-one has come through the well for nearly 500 years.
是的，就是一个大井。我们迷路了
Yeah well, here's the thing. We're a little lost.
你们都是超过24岁的长者
And you are all older than 24.
Ford?你多大了？
Ford? How old are you?
25岁
25 sir.
我猜是这样
I guess so.
有问题吗？
Is that a problem?
请坐
Please, sit.
Karris，他们是入侵者
我们没有必要向他们解释
They are trespassers Karris,
we don't have to explain ourselves.
我道歉
I apologise.
你们也知道幽灵吗？
You are familiar with the Wraith?
是的
Yes
但我们和幽灵不是朋友
Well we're not friends or anything like that.
幽灵过去侵占了我们的星球
The Wraith used to farm our planet.
就像我们过去豢养家禽和野兽一样
As we used to farm livestock and beasts of burden.
只有我们是他们的畜群
Only we were their herd.
是的，他们到哪里都那样做
Yeah, they seem to do that everywhere.
我们的祖先抗击过他们
但我们的武器不够先进
Our ancestors fought them,
but our weapons were not strong enough.
我们试着躲起来
但他们总能找到我们
Our people tried to hide from them,
but they were always found.
没有人能安乐的死去
没有人能得到永恒的安宁
None died peacefully.
None could enter into the eternal rest.
永恒的安宁？
Eternal rest?
死在幽灵的手里
To die at the hands of the Wraith.
在仇恨和邪恶中咽下最后一口气
To breathe your last breath amongst such hatred and evil.
你不可能安宁的去到另外一个世界
这就是命运
There is no way to move peacefully into
the next world, when that is your fate.
我们的先人认为要打败幽灵
必须要像幽灵那样思考
My ancestors decided that to beat the Wraith,
we must learn to think as they think.
我们决定不给幽灵留下任何一个有利用价值的人
We ensure that we never provide
the Wraith with a crop worth picking.
怎么做到？
By?
我们没有人活过24岁
None of us passes the age of 24.
用什么方法？
How do you manage that?
在我们25岁的前夜，我们就祭祀
On the eve of our 25th year, we make the sacrifice.
为了我们的族人和我们自己
能够安宁的进入另外一个世界
Both for our people and for our own
safe passage into the eternal rest.
什么？
What?
你们互相残杀？
You kill each other?
不，我们自行了断
No. We take our own lives.
所以幽灵已经500多年没有来这儿了
And so the Wraith have not returned for nearly 500 years.
我从来都没像现在这样觉得自己已经很老了
Never in my life have I ever felt so old.
毋庸置疑，这是我能想像到的最悲惨的生活
This is without a doubt, the most
screwed up way of life I can imagine.
他们好像已经习惯了
They seem to accept it.
他们只是孩子，怎么会知道呢？
They're kids, what do they know?
孩子们不希望我们在这儿
Kids that don't want to keep us around.
因为他们觉得我们的到来会引来幽灵
Because they believe our presence
may bring back the Wraith.
他们这么想是不对的，是吗？
They can't be right can they?
幽灵放过他们是因为他们还很小吗？
What the Wraith just ignore them,
because they're young?
我想起了小牛犊，是不是很相似
Reminds me of veal. Can't be the same thing can it?
当然不是，小牛肉很美味的
Of course not. Veal is delicious.
幽灵再也不来了是因为
他们的飞船一靠近这个村庄
The Wraith don't come by anymore,
because when their darts fly close to the villages,
电磁场就会干扰他们
the electro magnetic field takes them out.
就像干扰我们的飞船那样
Much like what happened to our Puddle Jumper.
他们为什么不在干扰之外的地方着陆
然后步行过来？
Why do they not just land outside
the disturbance and take the village by foot?
对不起，也许我没说清楚
任何东西在这儿都不起作用
I'm sorry, perhaps I'm not being clear.
Nothing works here!
他们的迷幻术、他们的飞船都不行
Not their stunners, their darts.
甚至连他们的防御设备也不能正常运行
Even their shields wouldn't function correctly.
我是说他们没必要冒这么大险
I mean, why would they risk their advantage,
因为通过星门还有很多地方有他们的猎物
when there's a smorgasbord,
through some other stargate?
我们的枪在这儿可以使用，是吗？
Our guns work though, right?
因为他们相对来说比较原始
他们不需要一个电磁场来启动
Because they're relatively primitive.
They don't generate an EM field.
我们必须告诉他们
We must tell them.
在我有机会检查这个古迹之前不要告诉他们
Not before I've had a chance
to look at those ruins, we don't.
他们毫无理由的自杀
They're sacrificing themselves for no reason.
Teyla，我们要告诉他们什么？
What are we going to tell them Teyla?
听着，孩子们！你们所相信的那些东西都是错的
Listen kiddies, everything you believe to be true is wrong,
相信我们吧，因为我们到这儿已经有一个小时了
and trust us, because we've been here for almost an hour.
我们讨论过了
你们可以呆在这儿，直到你们修好飞船
We've talked it over.
You can stay until you've fixed your ship.
但是你们必须快点
But you must work quickly.
你们来这儿让我们感觉很不舒服
Your being here makes our people uncomfortable.
这已经够公平了，我们尽快吧
That's fair enough. We'll work as quickly as we can.
在你们遇到我们的那个地方的古迹里
可能有些什么东西
There may have been something
in the ruins where you picked us up that,
使我们的飞船失去了控制
caused us to lose control of our ship.
他们任何时候都应该被监视
They should be watched at all times.
哦，不，很好！完全可以理解
No, no, no, that's fine. Totally understandable.
我会派两个村民来跟着你们
I'll choose two of the villagers to keep an eye on you.
Casta说你有100岁了，是吗？
Casta say's you're 100 years old. Are you?
谁是Casta？
Who's Casta?
我
Me.
Casta，你是从哪儿听来的？
Where are you getting your information Casta?
你们为什么要去那个古迹？
Why are you going to the old city?
- 我们要检查一些东西
- 什么东西？
- I gotta check something.
- What kind of thing?
这是大人的事情
It's grown up stuff.
什么是大人？
What's a grown up.
比你年长的人
Someone that's older than you are.
我比Claire大3岁，你告诉我吧
I'm 3 years older than Claire. You can tell me.
很好，但是你不是大人
Nice try, but you're not a grown up.
你刚刚说比我年长的人就是大人
But you just said,
someone that's older than me is a grown up.
我不需要你来告诉我我刚刚说了什么，好吗？
I don't need you to tell me what I just said, ok?
好
Ok
你们为什么要去那个古迹？
So, why are we going to the old city?
Ford，我需要你的救援
Ford, a little help here.
你在说什么？你是白痴
What are you talking about? You're a natural.
让我们来看看我们能多久不说话
Let's see how long we can be quiet.
谁会是最久的呢，嗯？
Who can be quiet the longest, huh?
哦，我是不是个安静的人?
Well, I'm not a quiet person.
那不是安静，你已经在说话了
That's not quiet. That's talking.
我不是个安静的人，我话很多
Well I'm not a quiet person. I talk a lot.
你有小孩吗？
You have young?
我？还没有，你呢？
Me? No. Not yet anyway. You?
我有了，他们在另外一个村子里
Oh yes. They're raised in one of the other villages.
另外一个村子？
Other villages?
延续我们家的香火
To keep family lines apart.
天啊，像这样的村子有多少个？
God. How many villages are there like this?
12个，他们都比这个要大一点
但是人数要少
Twelve. There are few larger than this one,
but, more smaller in number.
他们都自杀吗？
And they all make the sacrifice?
是的，我们都这样
就像我们先人那样
Yes. We all do. As have the many before.
没有人曾经……
No-one ever....
什么？
What?
就是决定打破这个规矩
离开这里或者逃走
Well, decides not to go through with it.
Takes off. Runs away.
我们有过犹豫
There has been hesitation.
我打赌
I bet.
只要时机合适，我们是可以被说服的
We can be persuasive when the time comes.
我知道这是什么意思
I know what that means
听着，我想告诉你
Look, I gotta tell you.
我完全不理解这是怎么回事
I don't understand this at all.
在我来的那个地方
我们珍惜生命超过一切
Where I come from, we value life
more than almost anything else.
Ford中尉，他只比你大1岁
Lt Ford, he's just a year older than you.
你知道如果他1年前就死了
他会错过多少美好的东西吗？
Do you know what he would have
missed out on if his life was over a year ago?
我们其实没有那么多不同
We're not all that different.
只是我宁愿拥有24年的宁静
也不愿意一辈子都活在恐惧里
It's just that I would rather have 24 years of peace,
than a life of fear.
但如果有另外一条出路呢？
What if there's another way.
自然，当时机到来的时候
Naturally, when the time comes.
时机到了
The time comes.
当然了，那是生命的一部分
Well of course it does, that's part of living a life.
我是说我自己
明天是我25岁的第一天
I mean for me. Tomorrows the first day of my 25th year.
明天？
Tomorrow?
是的，这就是为什么我是这里的头
Yes. That's why I lead the council of elders.
我是所有24岁的人中最大的
I'm oldest among the 24's.
你是说明天你要……
You mean tomorrow you um....
今晚
Tonight.
今晚？
Tonight?
我们的规定很久之前就定下来了，现在依然在执行
Our rule was put in place long ago, and it works.
这不容我去质疑
今晚我就要死了
It is not for me to question it. Tonight I die.
多少个人？
How many?
4个，他们说就他们4个
但是我们不敢肯定，也许更多
Four. They claim they're alone,
but we can't be sure. There may be more.
你给他们修飞船的时间了吗？
And you've given them time to repair the ship?
是的，这和我的想法正好相反
Against my strong objection, yes.
所以Karris
So this is Karris.
正在为自杀做准备了
没有心思考虑这些人的事情了
Who should be readying himself for sacrifice,
not troubling with the full growns.
明天我就是最大的了
但那可能太迟了
I will be the eldest by tomorrow,
but that may be too late.
你想干什么？
What do you want to do?
Louise，他们是从幽灵的那个大井里来的
They came through the Wraith well, Louise.
如果他们呆在这儿，幽灵就会来
那我们的牺牲就没有价值了
If they stay, the Wraith may come back,
and all our sacrifice may be for nothing.
我们需要立刻行动
强迫他们离开这里
This calls for action. They must be forced to leave.
我需要时间和其它村民讨论一些
I need time to talk to the other villages.
没时间了
We have little of it.
Aries，你是知道规则的
如果不让Karris知道这件事会很不好
You know the laws, Aries.
It's bad enough we're leaving Karris out of this.
强制的行动必须由村民们一致同意
A forced sacrifice must be agreed upon, by all the villages.
离我们远点
Leave us!
你爱和谁讨论就和谁讨论吧
Talk with who you need to talk.
我让他们今天就走
I will give them until the end of this day to leave.
如果他们不走……
If they do not....
嗨，嗨，让一下，谢谢！
Hey, hey. Coming through. Thankyou.
- 那是什么？
- 指南针
- What's that?
- It's a compass
- 指南针是什么？
- 在地球上用来辨别方向的
- What's that?
- Used for determining direction, on Earth.
- 我用它来……
- 地球在哪儿？
- I'm using it to....
- Where's Earth?
听着，Cleo？
Listen, Cleo?
Casta
叫什么都行，你们不是来监视的吗？
Whatever. Aren't you supposed to be observing.
知道什么叫监视吗？
Understand what that means? Observing?
监视？
Observing?
就是说他们让你们来观察
It means you're supposed to watch.
你们要离我们远一点，然后仔细观察
You're supposed to stay out of my way and watch.
为什么？
Why?
因为
Because
因为什么？
Because why?
因为是我说的
Because I say so.
为什么？
Why?
因为你们在我耳边吵来吵去问一些愚蠢的问题
我什么也干不了
Because I can't get any work done,
with you two buzzing around asking stupid questions,
还有你们愚蠢的声音
坐下来，闭嘴！
with your stupid little voices. Now sit down and shut up!
哦，别这样，别这样！
Oh don't. Don't.
你真粗鲁
You're mean
谢谢你们终于注意到这点了
Thankyou for finally noticing.
你们想死吗，你们想死吗，嗯？
Ok, you wanna go? You wanna go, huh?
好了，好了
你得到了孩子们真正的礼物
Ok, ok, ok. You've got a real gift with the kids, there.
你开过生日party吗？
Do you do birthday parties?
我还有事，你对付他们吧
让一让，谢谢！
Look, I have a purpose here.
You deal with them. Excuse me, thankyou.
没事了，没事了
因为你们比他聪明，所以他很恼火
It's ok. It's ok.
He's just upset because you're smarter than him.
你们知道什么是巧克力吗？
不知道？那给你们一个大大的惊喜吧
You guys know what chocolate is?
No? This is gonna be huge.
过来，我们到那儿去吧
让这个粗鲁的人自己呆着吧
Come on, we're gonna go over here,
and we're gonna leave the mean old man alone.
哦耶
Oh yeah.
好
Ok.
喂！喂！
Hello hello.
真好吃，还要吗？
Really Good. Hmmm More?
少校
Major!
McKay? 通话器可以用了
McKay? The radio's working.
我正在用它和你说话呢
Which is how I'm able to speak with you, yes.
你有空吗？
You have a second?
告诉我你找到了能量场发生器
Tell me you found the field generator.
我发现了能量场发生器
I found the field generator.
很明显，你把它关了
Obviously the off switch.
不仅如此
那个装置是由Z.P.M发动的
Better than that.
The device is powered by a Zero Point Module.
这绝对是几个世纪以来支撑能量场的东西
It's definitely the Em field has been online for centuries.
就我所知，只有Z.P.M才能支撑那么久
As far as I know, only a ZPm is
capable of powering it for that long.
我关掉了，一切恢复正常了
I've shut it down. Everything is working now.
你关闭了防御工事？
You've disabled the shield?
只是暂时的
Just temporarily.
我需要把Z.P.M带回亚特兰帝斯
我正在看这样做是否值得
I need to get the ZPM back to Atlantis.
See if it's worth taking.
我们不能把它带走
这个他们对付幽灵唯一的防御设备
We cannot just take it.
It is their only source of protection against the Wraith.
证据表明幽灵很多年没来这儿了
There's no evidence that
the Wraith have been here in years.
另外，这是一个完好的Z.P.M
Besides, this is a fully functioning ZPM.
我们要把它们都带回亚特兰帝斯
困难有多大？
We could bring them all back to Atlantis.
How hard could that be?
很困难，带走Z.P.M会有很多问题
Hard, but, a ZPM could make a lot of problems go away.
确实，我需要把它带回实验室
Exactly, I need to get it back to a lab.
你打算怎么做？
How do you plan on doing that?
我已经有合适的基因
而且你也给我上过飞行课
Well I've had the gene innoculation
and you've already given me a flying lesson.
问题远比那复杂
It's gonna take more than a shot
in the arm and a flying lesson.
听着，我要和幽灵进行空战
Listen, I'm not gonna be dogfighting Wraith darts.
我和Ford能够完成这个任务
Ford and I can handle it.
好吧，你们可以去
天黑之前要回我这儿
All right.
Fine, you can go. But get back to me before tonight?
他们给我们下了最后通牒
We sort of have a deadline.
好的
Right
我觉得让这些村子失去防御工事是很危险的
I think it is dangerous to leave the villages unprotected.
小孩们说得对
幽灵已经很久很久没来过了
The kids got a point.
The Wraith haven't been around in a very long time.
这样做很鲁莽，少校
This is reckless Major.
你必须明白这一点
You must see that.
放心，他们出现的几率有多大，
Common, what are the odds
they're going to show up...
在Mckay进行这些测试的这几个小时里？
...in the few hours it takes McKay
to run those tests?
这些向导为什么被送回村里？
Why were the guides sent back to the village?
是吗？
Were they?
是的
Yeah, they were.
也许到了午睡的时间了
Must have been nap time.
Sheppard，你觉得这是开玩笑吗？
You think this is a joke, Sheppard?
我不觉得周围发生的一切很可笑
I don't find much that's going
on around here, to be funny.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
两个成年人不在我们的监视范围内
Two of the full growns are out on watch.
Aries，你应该为今天晚上做准备了。
It's fine Aries. You should be getting ready for tonight, Karris.
净洗仪式就要开始了，你还没有……
The cleansing ceremony is set to begin,
and you haven't....
行了！我自己会准备的
Fine!
I'll go ready myself.
他们在讨论什么？
What were they talking about?
他今天晚上要自杀了
He's supposed to sacrifice himself tonight.
- Karris?
- 我试图劝他别这样做
-  I tried to talk him out of it.
如果我们告诉他们关于保护他们村子的防护层的事
If we tell them about the field
that protects their villages
我正在研究它
但现在我们什么也做不了
I'm working on that,
but we can't do anything
直到我们能找到处理zpm的方法
until we figure out what to do with the ZPM.
- Rodney，这是个很不好的电话
- 为什么?
- This is a very bad call Rodney
-  Why?
你刚刚告诉我说这个zpm
是他们对付幽灵的防御工事的发动器
You just told me that this ZPM empowers
their defences against the Wraith.
是啊
Yep.
你没看出来你的偷窃行为的问题？
You don't see the problem with stealing it?
这不是偷
It wouldn't be stealing so much as...
如果对我们有用，我们就可以把它拿来用
Look if it's any good to us,
we can bring them here.
好吧，首先，我们甚至不知道他们有多少人
Alright, for one
We don't even know how many of them there are.
我怀疑有几百人
Well I highly doubt there'd be more than a few hundred.
什么？
嗨，我们是自己来这的
What?
Hey, we're barely getting by here ourselves
这是个很大的空城
而我们拥有整个大陆
This is a big empty city,
and we have the mainland now.
Rodney, 我们不能来到别的星球
然后把它们的防御设备带走
Rodney, we can't just visit planets,
take away their defences,
只有它们对我们有用
我们就把它们带回亚特兰帝斯
Look if it's any good to us,
we can bring them here to Atlantis.
如果他们能拥有zpm，我们也可以
If they have a ZPM, yes we can.
哦，天啊，你觉得你在道德上很优越嘛！
Oh my god,
how morally superior you must feel.
伊丽莎白，他们住在树上
Elizabeth, they live in trees.
亚特兰帝斯对他们来说又前进了一大步
Atlantis would be a big step up for them.
而且他们还毫无理由的自杀
Plus they could stop killing
themselves for no good reason.
而且他们还毫无理由的自杀？
Are they killing themselves for no good reason?
是的
电磁场是幽灵不敢侵犯的原因
Yes they are.
The EM shield is what's keeping the Wraith away.
而不是他们的自杀
Not the sacrificing.
好，你说他们的自杀大约始于
Ok, you said that the sacrifices
began at about the same time,
- 那个防御工事生效的时候
- 应该是这样
- you think the shield went online.
-  More or less
那修建这个防御工事的人
So if the people that built the shield
are the same people
是否就是制定这个自杀政策的人
that implemented the suicide pact,
也许这两者并非你想像的那样毫无关连
perhaps the two things aren't
as disconnected as you think.
也许
Maybe.
我只需要再多给我们一天时间
我就会了解得很清楚
One more day, that's all I need.
I'll have a much clearer picture then.
了解什么？
A picture of what?
说来话长，跟着我，我就告诉你
Long story.
Stick around and I'll tell you.
Sheppard，我会很诚实的
I'll be honest with you Sheppard.
再没什么比跟你说话
更让我喜欢的了
There's nothing I'd like more, than to spend more time talking with you.
但不可能
But it's not possible.
如果你们错了呢？
What if you're wrong?
如果一天并不重要呢？
What if a day doesn't matter?
如果一年也不重要呢？
What if a year doesn't matter?
如果重要呢？
And what if it does?
我肯定不会活得很安宁
I'd never rest peacefully knowing that
如果我是导致幽灵来到这个星球的罪魁祸首
I was the reason the Wraith came to this planet.
-你本可以过一个完整的一生
-你是你们星球的一个军人
- You could live a full life.
-  You're a warrior among your people.
被训练用来防卫敌人保护星球了
One who is trained to defend and protect them.
我想可以这么说
I guess you could say that.
如果必要时，你愿意牺牲自己的生命吗？
Would you not willingly give your life
if it were necessary?
如果真正需要的话
It'd have to be really necessary.
那自杀有什么不同？
How is the sacrifice so different?
所以这个规定要一直延续下去，永远
So this is just gonna go on forever.
只要幽灵不回来
As long as the Wraith don't return.
是的
Yes.
你愿意观看吗？
Would you stand witness?
我？
Me?
我需要做点什么吗？
Well what do I have to do.
只要在那就可以了，当我准备好的时候
Just be there as I prepare.
我们从身边的人那里吸取力量
We gather the strength from those close to us,
等待祭祀的来临
for the sacrifice to come.
Weir 博士，坏消息
Dr Weir.
The bad news,
看起来那个装置只能利用M7G677这个唯一的电磁场
is it looks like the device harnesses M7G677 unique electro magnetic field.
很可能对我们没什么用
It probably wouldn't work for us.
我们偷它本来就不对
Assuming we were considering stealing it.
不是这个问题
这个Z.P.M几乎已经坏了
Not much point to that either.
The ZPM is almost depleted.
所以没什么用？
So it's worthless?
不好说，它足够给我们的
I wouldn't say that.
It's enough to give us
防御设备提供几个小时的能量
the shield at full power
for a few hours,
如果幽灵来的话就会有用
which would be handy if
the Wraith were to attack.
如果按照原来的方式它会撑得很久，但是……
Now it can continue what it's being
doing for quite some time but....
所以这对他们比对我们更有用
So it's of more worth to them,
than it is to us.
很可能
Probably.
- 很明显就是这样！
- 好吧
- Definitely!
-  Fine.
-还有件事
-嗯？
- There's another thing.
-  Uh-huh?
我想我可以解释这种自杀行为
I think I have a theory about the suicide pact.
是吗？什么？
Yeah, what is it?
我不知道这个装置启动时有多大能量
I'm not sure how much power
this thing had to start with,
但是建造这个电磁装备的人，
肯定知道它不会撑得太久
but whoever built the EM device,
knew it wouldn't be able to power the field,
如果给整个星球的防御工事供应能量的话
large enough to cover
the whole planet for very long.
所以它是用来保护一小片区域的
So it was built to protect a smaller area.
或者是围绕着这些村庄的区域
More or less,
the area around the villages.
但如果人数太多的话
But if the population
got much larger than they are now,
很可能孩子们就会来到防御工事之外的地方
there's a chance the kids
would move out of the field
成为幽灵的袭击对象
and become susceptible to a Wraith attack.
所以这种自杀规定是一种
So the suicide pact is....
人口控制
Population control.
-哇呜，那就有点严重了
-有点？
-  Wow, that's a little severe.
-  A little?
问题是他们相信
如果他们死于恐惧和战争
The point is that they believe
if they die in fear and turmoil,
他们就不能进入他们自己版本的天堂
they don't get to go to
their version of heaven.
现在他们这么做至少能保证安宁的死去
Now while this, at the very least,
guarantee's that they die in peace,
这是一种，一种宗教
很荒谬的那种
it's a... well it's a religion,
and a pretty ridiculous one at that.
我们没有权利评价他们
Well that's not a judgement
that we can make for them.
没有？
- No?
-没有
- No
我希望你和Ford中尉将这个Z.P.M还回去
No, and I'd like you and Lt Ford
to return the ZPM,
让他们的装置重新运行起来
and get their device back online.
Sheppard, 我是 McKay.
Sheppard, it's McKay.
我是 Teyla
Sheppard少校无法接通话器
This is Teyla.
Major Sheppard is unavailable.
什么意思？
What does that mean?
Karris 邀请他参加净洗仪式
Karris has asked him to take part
in the cleansing ceremony.
- 不是件好事
- 你回来了吗？
- That doesn't sound good.
-  Are you back?
我和Ford回到了古迹那儿
我正要把zpm放回去
Ford and I are back in the old city.
I'm just going to put the ZPM back.
好，我会告诉Sheppard 少校
Good, I'll let Major Sheppard know.
我把飞船停在电磁场外面
一弄完我们就可以走了
I've parked the Jumper outside the EM field,
so we'll leave as soon as I've finished.
Teyla!
Sheppard 少校发现了一个幽灵的臂镯
已经开始能量传输了
Major Sheppard has found a Wraith bracelet
that has already begun transmitting.
我们需要以最快的速度
恢复电磁场
We need that field returned,
as soon as possible.
阻止它！
Stop him!
对不起，我必须那么做
I'm sorry, I had to do that.
McKay. 我们需要恢复地磁场, 现在!
McKay. We need it on, now!
-快跑！
-我来了
- Move!
-  I'm coming!
-你在等什么？
-应该就是这个
- Well what are you waiting for?
-  That should be it.
-是哪个？
-还好我没引起一场灾难
- That should be what?
-  Far be it for me to cause a panic.
你干什么了？你干什么了？
What did you do? What did you do?
我想我有可能，一念之间毁了它
I think there's the slightest possibility, that in my haste, I might have broken it.
你怎么敢亵渎我们的纪念品？
How dare you defile our remembrance.
-我必须那么做
-必须？
- It was necessary.
-  Necessary?
你违法了这的规矩，必须受到惩罚
You broke the laws, you must be punished.
-这不由你决定，Aries
-也不再由你来决定了
- It's not up to you Aries.
-  Neither is it up to you anymore.
你们有足够的时间
你们修好飞船就滚吧
You've had enough time.
You must fix your ship and go!
他们希望我们拿自己的生命开玩笑开多久？
How long do they expect us
to play chance with our lives?
只要他们中一个人还在我们的村子里
Every second a full grown is in our village,
我们就不能安全的躲过幽灵
is a second we are no longer safe
from the Wraith.
他们必须现在就离开
They must leave now.
我带你们去大井那儿
你们在这不安全
I'll take you to the well.
You're not safe here.
-McKay 和Ford还在森林里
-我们中途去接他们
- McKay and Ford are in the woods.
-  We'll pick them up on the way.
- 他把zpm放回去了吗？
- 没有成功
- Has he put the ZPM back? What did McKay do?
- There's been a setback.
朋友们，别这样！
Friends! Please!
他们已经同意离开了
而且永远不再回来
The full growns have agreed to
leave and never come back.
我会带他们去大井那儿，我一个人去
I will take them to the well, myself.
这一切即将结束
我们可以继续我们的仪式
All this will be over soon,
and we can get on with the ceremony.
确保他们真的回到那儿
Make sure they get there.
告诉我你让它重新启动了
Please tell me you have this working.
我不知道我干什么了
这玩意平常只是插上去然后运行就可以了
I don't know what I did.
These things just usually plug and play.
-这个装置可能使用另外一个平台
-说简单点
- This device must be using a different window.
- Get to the point.
我是说，安装zpm需要一个程序，但我还没掌握
What I'm saying is, there is a sequence
to installing a ZPM, that I haven't got yet.
这不重要了，你们快点跟我走吧
None of that matters now, just grab
what you can and come with me.
Aries 会派人跟踪我们
Aries will be sending men behind us.
是什么让臂镯开始接通的？
What made the bracelet start broadcasting?
我想不是我们造成的
I do not think it was anything we did.
很可能是一种警报
就像飞船坠毁时会启动那样
It's possible it was like an emergency beacon
that activated when the dart crashed.
从那以后电磁场的存在让它变得很安静
The EM field's been keeping it quiet ever since.
但Mckay关掉电磁场的时候
它就开始传输信息
It must have begun transmitting
as soon as McKay turned off the field.
听着，我们必须现在就走！
Listen to me.
We have to move on now!
我们不能那样做
We cannot do that.
Karris, 这很难解释，但我不如果不修好它就哪也不能去
-我们
- Karris, this is hard to explain,
but we can't go anywhere till we fix this device.
- We
你们刚刚扔掉了飞船
如果留在这会有生命危险
You'll just have to abandon your ship.
You're risking your lives if you stay.
这跟我们的飞船无关
This is not about our ship.
这是关于你们村子的防御工事
This is about the protection of your villages.
什么？
What?
Karris, 我们飞船毁坏的原因
Karris, the reason our ship went down.
和当年幽灵船坠毁的原因一样
都是这个装置引起的
The reason the Wraith dart crashed
so long ago, is because of this device.
它屏蔽了所有依赖电磁场的技术
It renders all electro magnetic based
technology inside the shield, inert.
我不明白
I don't understand.
他们是说幽灵没有入侵
不是因为你们的祭祀
What they're saying is that the Wraith didn't
stay away because of your sacrifices.
而是因为这个防御层
They stayed away because of this shield.
这不是真的
That can't be true.
这全部都是真的
防御层不能保护整个星球
It's not entirely true actually.
The shield doesn't protect the whole planet,
它没有那么多能量
我相信祭祀的主意
it doesn't have enough power.
I believe the idea of the sacrifice,
是让你们的种族不要远离
防御层的保护
was brought in so that your society
never left the confines of the shield.
你瞧，祭祀对于你们的生存确实有重要的作用
但是不是你们所相信的那个原因
Look, the sacrifices play a part in your survival,
but not for the reasons you believe.
不可能
That's impossible.
我可以证明给你看
但你必须给我时间，让这个装置恢复正常
I can prove it to you. But you have to give us
time to bring this device back online.
Karris很软弱
我怀疑他不敢献身
Karris is weak.
I doubt his oath to the sacrifice.
那些成年人影响了他的判断力
The full growns have clouded his judgement.
他们还在古迹那儿，并没有离开
They've stopped in the old city and are not moving on.
拿起弓和箭
Get the bows and the spears.
我们现在就把他们驱逐出去
永远不让他们回来
We will rid ourselves of them now,
once and for all!
借过，借过，让一下
Coming through, coming through.
Excuse me.
好吧，再让一下，谢谢
Alright.
And again, still in the way, thankyou.
这肯定没什么用
This will never work.
我们别无选择
We don't have much of a choice.
Karris，这可不是大井
This is not the well, Karris
我的错
It's my fault.
我们刚刚得到McKay的消息
我们的飞船修好了
We just received word from McKay,
that our ship's just been repaired.
事实上，他现在已经在飞船那儿等着我们了
In fact, he's back there right now,
waiting for us.
我们刚刚在和Karris说再见
We were just saying goodbye to Karris.
你觉得我是个傻子吗？
You think I am a fool?
不，我只是觉得你有点猜疑
No. I just think you're a little cranky.
看，如果你想让我们去飞船那儿
你可以看着我们离开
Look! If you want to escort us back to the ship,
you can watch us leave.
带路
Lead the way.
哦，你吓到我了
Oh, you scared me!
是你吓到我们了
You scared us!
- 对不起
- 没关系
- I'm sorry.
- That's ok.
我们想过来看看你们有没有留下点巧克力
We came to see if you left any chocolate.
哦，当然留下了
Yes, yes, of course.
什么？
What?
哦，你们想要点巧克力
Oh, you want some.
好，给你们这个
Ok, well you can have this,
但你们要保证让我工作，好吗？
but you gotta promise to let me work ok?
- 好
- 好的
- Ok.
- All right.
安静点
Quietly.
你想留McKay一个人在那儿吗？
Do you intend to leave McKay behind?
我们在周围环绕飞行
直到他修好机器，他会来的
We'll circle around until he get's
the device back on. He'll show up.
太晚了
我们太迟了
It's too late.
We're too late!
那个鬼东西是什么？
What the hell was that?
它太小，不可能是飞船
It was too small to be a dart.
可能是某种探测器
It was a probe of some kind.
也许是来检查一下幽灵臂镯发出的信号
Probably came to check out the signal
from the Wraith bracelet.
在它回到星门前
我们要把它击落
We have to take it down before
it gets back to the gate.
朋友们？
Boys?
我们要把那个探测器击落
否则会有大麻烦
Let us take that probe down,
or we're all in deep trouble.
即使你们能击落它
也会来更多的
Even if you were able to destroy it,
more will come
不是这样的
That is not true
Sheppard，你认为它们为什么会在这儿？
Why do you think they're here Sheppard?
是因为你们，幽灵感觉到了猎物的存在
他们要来狩猎了
You. The Wraith have sensed a crop worth harvesting,
and they've come to claim it.
Karris，你告诉他们，我们要把这个东西击落
在它飞回星门之前
Karris, tell them, that we gotta take this thing down,
before it get's back to the Stargate.
还有一个成年人在哪里？
Where's the other full grown?
Aries
Aries,
有一个装置保护我们不受幽灵的袭击
there's a device that shields us
from the machines of the Wraith.
- 祭祀很可能是……
- 他肯定在古迹那儿，走！
- The sacrifices might have been....
-  He'll be in the old city, go!
Aries, 听我说
Aries, listen to me.
Karris，你不敢献身
你将我们都置于危险之中了
You've let your fear of the sacrifice,
put our entire people in danger, Karris.
你们是受到一个防御层的保护
才躲过幽灵的
You have been protected from the Wraith,
by a shield.
我们碰巧把它关闭了
We turned it off by accident.
好消息是如果我们重新启动它
But the good news is,
that if we get it back up,
幽灵就再也不会来了
the Wraith will never come again.
只有一个方法可以确保幽灵不会再来
There's only one thing I have to do,
to make sure the Wraith never come again.
就是杀死你
Kill you.
帮帮忙
Come on.
有人来了
Somebody is coming.
这是什么？
What is this?
- 你必须现在就跟我们走
- 我不能那样做
- You must come with us now!
-  I can't do that.
听着，我需要在这儿完成我的工作
Listen!
I need to finish my work here.
我见过幽灵侵犯别的星球
他们根本不在乎你们有多大
I've seen how the Wraith deal with other planets,
and they don't care how old you are.
我要重新启动这个装置
很快就能完了
I need to get this device turned on,
and I am so close to figuring it out.
给我一点时间吧
So just give me one more shot.
听着，你们俩
回到你们的屋子里去
Look, both of you.
Go to your rooms!
你们不听是吗？
You're not buying this are you?
喂，嘘
过来，过来
Hey, psst.
Come on, come on.
不
No.
长官，我不希望变成这样
Sir.
I don't like where this is headed.
没事的，Ford
Easy Ford.
刚刚没人开枪
Nobody's shooting just yet.
但是……
Yet...
也没有人打算要开枪
And nobody's going to either.
Aries, 你根本不知道你们要面临的是什么
Aries, you have no idea
what you're up against here.
我们的武器比你们所见过的要先进很多
The weapons we carry are more powerful
than any you have ever seen.
她说的是实话
She's telling the truth.
它们不仅仅是只能发出大的响动
而且它们能杀死你们
They do more than make a lot of noise,
they will kill you.
它起作用了
It works.
- 当然它能起作用
- 我要告诉Aries，跟我们来
- Of course it works.
- I must tell Aries. Come with us.
嗨，你们还好吗？
Hey, you guys ok?
回村子里去吧
就没事了
Head back to the village,
you're going to be fine.
你们的存在引来了幽灵
Your presence has brought the Wraith.
我们的先人祭祀
你们确破坏了这一切
All our ancestors sacrifices,
you've undone!
这都是因为你们没按我们说的离开这
All because you refused to leave
when you were told to.
并不是那么简单
It's not that simple.
就是那么简单
Yeah it is that simple
- Aries, 不!
- Karris!
- Aries, no!
-  Karris!
- 长官
- 别开枪
- Sir!
- Hold your fire!
看看你做了什么
Look what you've done.
他和你一样有罪
He's as guilty as you are.
Ford?
准备好了，长官
Ready sir.
我们要自卫了
We will defend ourselves.
相信我，你们也不想那样
And believe me,
you don't want that.
准备弓箭
Archers ready!
它起作用了
It works!
Aries!
它起作用了
It works!
那个装置起作用了
The device works!
他们说的那个装置是真的
我亲眼见了
The device they speak of is real.
I've seen it.
什么？
What?
McKay修好了它
幽灵的鸟从天上掉下来了
McKay fixed it and the Wraith
bird fell right out of the sky.
- 这不重要了
- Aries！它确实有用
- That doesn't matter.
-  Aries! It works.
你没事吧，McKay?
You alright McKay?
我快喘不过气了
Gotta catch my breath.
从飞船里拿药箱来
他会没事的
Get the medical kit from the jumper.
It'll be ok.
如果没有能量增长的话
它能够覆盖50%的区域
Was able to boost the coverage by over
50% without much of a power increase,
所以可以让很多人生存
so there should be enough
for a sizeable population growth.
谢谢
Thank you.
但是你也不知道这个防御层能维持多久吗？
But you have no idea how long the shield will last?
不知道，很可能等你当爷爷了还能维持
There's no way of knowing, but there's a good
chance you'll be grandparents before it goes.
我们会很愿意经常回来看看你
We'll be happy to come back and check
in on you every now and again.
事实上Ford是很愿意回来解释一下怎么活到25岁的
In fact Ford will be happy to come back
and explain how to be a 25 year old.
- 我等待那一天
- 你们必须习惯一些事情
- I'll look forward to it.
- You'll have to get used to a few things,
既然这儿所有的都改变了
now that everything's changing around here.
但是我们下次来的时候可以讨论这个问题
But we can talk about that next time we visit.
答应我，你要跟着我
Just promise me you'll stick around.
我会的
I will.
所有的村民都同意取消祭祀了吗？
Have all the villages agreed to
suspend the sacrifices?
需要我们改变一些规矩
但是现在……是的
It will require us to change some laws,
but for now.... Yes.
- 长官
- 这个给你
- Sir
- Oh right, here
这是什么？
What's this?
在我们那个星球上
当你长大了1岁就会收到礼物
Well where we're from, you get presents
when you turn a year older.
盯着他，在那儿
See him, there.
生日快乐
Happy birthday.
你们去那儿吧
There you go
给你一个
One for you.